<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//DLDC//DTD Revised TEI DTD for Goodspeed Manuscript Project//EN"
"http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/bus/DTD/goodspeed.dtd">
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader date.created="2015-11-04" creator="jfcd">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[University of Chicago Library GMS-0131, a manuscript catalogue description in electronic form]</title>
                <funder>Institute of Museum and Library Services</funder>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic version:</resp>
                    <name>University of Chicago Library</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Chicago Library</name>
                </respStmt> 
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Chicago Library, Special Collections Research Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
                <date>2009</date>
                <idno type="Local">http://pi.lib.uchicago.edu/1001/dig/gms/0131</idno>
                <availability status= "free">
                    <p>Publicly accessible</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDescription>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>United States</country>
                        <region>Illinois</region>
                        <settlement>Chicago</settlement>
                        <institution>University of Chicago Library</institution> 
                        <repository>Special Collections Research Center</repository>
                        <collection>Goodspeed Manuscript Collection</collection>
                        <idno>Ms. 131</idno>
                        <altName type="Gregory number">Greg. 2394</altName>
                        <altIdentifier type="former shelfmark">Goodspeed Ms. Grk. 7</altIdentifier></msIdentifier>
                    <msHeading>
                        <title>New Testament. Gospels</title>
                        <otherName>Chrysanthus Gospels</otherName>
                        <origPlace>Balkan Peninsula?</origPlace>
                        <origDate notBefore="1101" notAfter="1300">12th or 13th century</origDate>
                        <textLang langKey="grc">Greek</textLang>
                        <textLang langKey="ell">Greek</textLang>
                        <textLang langKey="chu">Church Slavonic</textLang>
                    </msHeading>
                    <msContents> 
                        <overview><p>Four gospels in Greek. Ammonian section and Eusebian canon numbers in the margins. Added tables to calculate the dates of Easter. 
                            Formerly Goodspeed Ms. Grk. 7.</p></overview>
                    </msContents>
                    <decoration><overview>
                        <p>The manuscript contains 6 Evangelist portraits, 3 original and 3 added at an unknown date. Portraits of the Evangelist Matthew are lost.</p>
                    </overview> <canonTables>
                        <p>Citations of concordant gospel sections are framed by architectural columns. These support arched headpieces of multi-colored floral, foliate, and geometric designs. 
                            Drawings of lions in red added to the headpiece of the first table.</p>
                    </canonTables>
                        <headpieces><p>Headpiece of Matthew (fol. 12r), square panel topped with two peacocks; central roundel, Christ in Majesty, right hand raised in blessing. Four 
                            creatures (angel, eagle, ox, and lion) in small roundels, one in each corner. Headpieces of the other Evangelists embellished with 
                            floral, foliate, and geometric motifs in blue, red, and gold at each gospel opening (fols. 125r, 195r, and 314r).</p>
                        </headpieces>
                        <initials>
                            <p>Beta, the major initial of Matthew, is formed from intertwined figures of men and animals (35-40 mm). Zacharias the priest holding a censer represents the epsilon 
                                of Luke's opening. The initials of Mark and John are not decorated (20-25 mm). Minor initials in red set off from the text.</p>
                        </initials>
                    </decoration>
                    <physDesc>
                        <support><p><material>Parchment</material> and <material>paper</material>. <dimensions type="block" units="mm">200 x 140 mm</dimensions>.</p></support>
                        <extent>401 leaves, of which 1 is a partially raised pastedown and two are flyleaves of paper that function as Easter tables.</extent>
                        <foliation><p>1 (unfoliated paper pastedown) + 2 (foliated paper flyleaves) + 398. Modern foliation in Arabic numerals in pencil 1-400.</p></foliation>
                        <collation><p>49 quires of 8 leaves, with the exception of quire 48 of 6 leaves, quires 15, 30, and 37 of 7 leaves, and quires 1 and 49 of 10 leaves. Estimate of content lost: 
                            leaf 10 of quire 1 and a bifolium (after fol. 11, original and later portraits of Matthew); 1 leaf of quire 15 (after fol. 121, kephalaia of Mark).</p> 
                            <p>A second set of 4 Evangelist portraits was added at an unknown date, and 3 leaves of paper containing tables to determine the dates of Easter.</p></collation>
                        <dimensions type="written" units="mm">Written space 150 x 105 mm (fol. 29r).</dimensions> 
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="16-20"><p>1 column, 16 to 20 lines. Ruling with hard point. Lines previously ruled on the bifolium fols. 141 and 148 stand 
                            at right angles to the lines of the later ruling pattern.</p></layout>
                        <msWriting><handDesc script="Minuscule" medium="ink"><p>Written in minuscule script in black to dark brown ink (some flaking).</p>
                            <p>Punctuation includes middle point, comma, marks of elision and interrogation. Quotation marks in left margin next to each line of quoted text.</p></handDesc>
                        </msWriting>
                        <textDivisions><p>Titles and lectionary indicators αρχε (beginning) and τελος (end) in red.</p></textDivisions>
                        <condition><p>Leaves trimmed resulting in the loss of some text. Moderately cockled. Dirt and water stains.</p></condition>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding><p>Bound in red <material>velvet</material> over boards. Floral-patterned edge decoration, fore-edge in blue. Doublures (one remaining, back) of 
                                woven cloth in a diagonal pattern of rose, white, blue, and yellow, bordered with strips of rose silk glued down.</p></binding></bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history><origin><p>The manuscript may have been written in the <name reg="Balkan Peninsula" type="place">Balkan Peninsula</name> to judge from certain of the inscriptions, and in either the 12th or 13th century.</p></origin> 
                        <provenance><p>Medieval to late 17th century provenance unknown. Contains dated and undated colophons and inscriptions in Greek and Church Slavonic.</p>
                            <p><name reg="Kosma" type="person" role="monk">Kosma</name>, a hieromonk of <name reg=" Monastery of Chilandari (Mount Athos, Greece)" type="org">Hilandar</name>, the Serbian monastery  
                                on <name reg="Mount Athos, Greece" type="place">Mount Athos</name>, restored the manuscript when it belonged to the <name reg="Church of St. George (Pološko)" type="org">Church of St. George, Pološko</name>, which today is 
                                located near <name reg="Kavadarci, Macedonia" type="place">Kavadarci</name> in the <name reg="Macedonia" type="place"> Republic of Macedonia</name> (undated inscription written 
                                by <name reg="Michael the Painter" type="person" role="artist">Michael the Painter</name>; prayer of Kosma, fol. 9v).</p>
                            <p>The manuscript was in the possession of <name reg="Chekhra" type="person" role="monk">Chekhra</name>, chief monk of Kovin, who documented the transfer of his authority over the 
                                <name reg="Church of St. Nicholas (Kovin)" type="org">Church of St. Nicholas</name> to the Bishop <name reg="Nicholas" type="person" role="bishop">Nicholas</name> in an undated inscription (fol. 400v).</p>
                            <p>At the end of the 17th century, the book was rebound and restored by the hieromonk <name reg="Chrysanthus, 17th century" type="person" role="monk">Chrysanthus</name>, whose inscription notes that he took it 
                                from a Turkish-controlled area of <name reg="Iberia" type="place">Iberia</name>, the present-day nation of <name reg="Georgia" type="place">Georgia</name> (his inscription, fol. 2v). Both Chrysanthus's inscription and 
                                a second unsigned writing dated 11 February 1700 (fol. 123v) include the name Τζηλτηρε, a geographic area as yet unidentified.</p>
                            <p>The monk Kosma's signature with two gospel citations (fol. 10r); inscription of <name reg="Gerasim" type="person">Gerasim</name> (fol. 400v, undated); prayer of <name reg="Singchoreseos" type="person" role="monk">Singchoreseos</name> 
                                (front pastedown, recto, undated); unsigned and undated inscriptions and prayers (fols. 4r, 6r, 122r, 147r, 400v). Drawings of birds (front pastedown, verso).</p></provenance>
                        <acquisition><p>Acquired by the University of Chicago in 1929 from <name reg="Riefstahl, Rudolf Meyer, 1880-1936" type="person" role="antiquarian">Rudolf M. Riefstahl</name> 
                            (New York), with funds provided by <name reg="Woodward, Frederic Campbell, 1874-1954" type="person" role="donor">Frederic C. Woodward</name>, 
                            university vice-president, <name reg="Matthews, Shailer, 1863-1941" type="person" role="donor">Shailer Matthews</name>, dean of the Divinity School, calligrapher and illuminator 
                            <name reg="Ricketts, Coella Lindsay, 1859-1941" type="person" role="donor">Coella Lindsay Ricketts</name>, and real estate 
                            developer <name reg="Galt, Arthur T., born 1876" type="person" role="donor">Arthur T. Galt</name>.</p></acquisition>
                    </history></msDescription>
            </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Edgar J. Goodspeed Manuscript Collection contains 68 Greek, Armenian, Latin, Syriac, Ethiopic, and 
                    Arabic manuscripts, which range in date from the fifth to the nineteenth century. With support from the Institute 
                    of Museum and Library Services National Leadership Grants for Libraries, Building Digital Resources program, 
                    the University of Chicago Library has created the online Goodspeed Manuscript Collection, a unique digital 
                    resource with manuscripts digitized in their entirety and presented with high-quality zoomable images through 
                    an interface that supports browsing within individual manuscripts and across the collection.</p>
                <p>Descriptions of the manuscripts have been encoded using the standard set forth in TEI Consortium, eds., <title>TEI P5 Guidelines for Electronic 
                    Text Encoding and Interchange: Manuscript Description</title>, at <ref>http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html</ref> 
                    as of <date>2012-09-22</date>.</p> 
                <p>The TEI DTD used was obtained from the Digital Scriptorium of Columbia University 
                    at, <ref>https://www1.columbia.edu/sec/cu/libraries/bts/digital_scriptorium/technical/ds-xml/description_dtd/index.html</ref> on <date>2012-09-22</date>. To 
                    accommodate specific project needs, the DTD was edited and extended with local tags in order to describe the content of miniatures, 
                    and the structure of canon tables, headpieces, and initials. The process of editing included equating the element Decoration with the seven 
                    recognized elements of the TEI Manuscript Description, not only to emphasize intellectual substance, but also to augment 
                    visibility by providing links from the record through encoding to the digitized imagery of the Web display.</p> 
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage><language id="grc"></language><p>Greek, Ancient (to 1453), ISO 639-3</p></langUsage>
            <langUsage><language id="ell"></language><p>Greek, Modern (1453-), ISO 639-3</p></langUsage>  
            <langUsage><language id="chu"></language><p>Church Slavonic, ISO 639-3</p>
 </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>Bible. N.T. Gospels. Greek</term>
                    <term>Bible--Manuscripts</term>
                    <term>Miniatures (Illuminations)</term>
                    <term>Chrysanthus, 17th century</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
 </profileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
  <text>
  <body>
<msDescription id="GMS-0131">
<msIdentifier>
<country>United States</country>
<region>Illinois</region>
<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
<institution>University of Chicago Library</institution> 
<repository>Special Collections Research Center</repository>
<collection>Goodspeed Manuscript Collection</collection>
    <idno>Ms. 131</idno>
    <altName type="Gregory number">Greg. 2394</altName>
    <altIdentifier type="former shelfmark">Goodspeed Ms. Grk. 7</altIdentifier></msIdentifier>
    <msHeading>
        <title>New Testament. Gospels</title>
        <otherName>Chrysanthus Gospels</otherName>
        <origPlace>Balkan Peninsula?</origPlace>
        <origDate notBefore="1101" notAfter="1300">12th or 13th century</origDate>
        <textLang langKey="grc">Greek</textLang>
        <textLang langKey="ell">Greek</textLang>
        <textLang langKey="chu">Church Slavonic</textLang>
    </msHeading>
<msContents> 
    <overview><p>Four gospels in Greek. Ammonian section and Eusebian canon numbers in the margins. Added tables to calculate the dates of Easter. 
        Formerly Goodspeed Ms. Grk. 7.</p></overview>
<msItem n="1">
    <locus from = "002" to ="002">Pastedown (front)</locus>
    <locus from = "003" to ="008">fols. 1r-3v</locus>
     <summary>Tables for calculating the dates of Easter.</summary>
</msItem>
    <msItem n="2">
        <locus from = "006" to ="006">fol. 2v</locus> 
        <colophon>The hieromonk Chrysanthus, dated 1700.</colophon>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="3">
        <locus from = "009" to ="009">fol. 4r</locus> 
        <summary>Eusebius of Caesarea, ca. 260-ca. 340, Letter to Carpianus, on the Gospel Canons (lacking).</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="4">
        <locus from = "010" to ="019">fols. 4v-9r</locus>
        <summary>Canon tables I-X.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="5">
        <locus from = "021" to ="021">fol. 10r</locus> 
        <colophon>I hieromonk and priest Kosma came to Pološko to the Church of Saint George from Hilandar of the Holy Mountain
            and having found books of the Eucharistion ... [?] there began with zeal and labor and repaired the four Gospels the Acts of the 
            Apostles the Tridion and the Psalter. Michael the Painter has written this. God have mercy on Kosma.</colophon>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="6">
        <locus from = "022" to ="024">fols. 10v-11v</locus> 
        <summary>Kephalaia of Matthew.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="7">
        <locus from = "025" to ="244">fols. 12r-121v</locus> 
        <summary>Matthew. Subscription.</summary> 
        <note>Blank (fols. 123r, 124r).</note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="8">
        <locus from = "251" to ="380">fols. 125r-189v</locus> 
        <summary>Mark.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="9">
        <locus from = "381" to ="385">fols. 190r-192r</locus> 
        <summary>Kephalaia of Luke.</summary> 
        <note>Blank (fols. 193r-194r).</note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="10">
        <locus from = "391" to ="617">fols. 195r-308r</locus> 
        <summary>Luke. Subscription.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="11">
        <locus from = "617" to ="621">fols. 308r-310r</locus> 
        <summary>Prologue of John.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="12">
        <locus from = "621" to ="623">fols. 310r-311r</locus> 
        <summary>Kephalaia of John. Stichoi (2,300).</summary> 
        <note>Blank (fols. 312r-313r).</note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="13">
        <locus from = "629" to ="801">fols. 314r-400r</locus> 
        <summary>John. Subscription.</summary>
    </msItem>
    <msItem n="14">
        <locus from = "802" to ="802">fol. 400v</locus> 
        <colophon>I believe in one God almighty creator of heaven and earth. I 
            Chekhra chief monk of Kovin transmit my church of St. Nicholas to the rule of my Lord 
            Bishop Nicholas. Whoever wishes to take it away from him let him be cursed by him 
            by the holy council and by Saint Nicholas to eternity. Amen.</colophon>
    </msItem>
</msContents>
    <decoration><overview>
        <p>The manuscript contains 6 Evangelist portraits, 3 original and 3 added at an unknown date. Portraits of the Evangelist Matthew are lost.</p>
    </overview>
        <miniatures><minItem n="1"> 
            <locus from ="246" to="246">fol. 122v</locus>
            <minDesc>Evangelist, Mark, Portrait: Mark reading book on lectern, seated on bench.</minDesc></minItem>
             <minItem n="2"> 
                <locus from ="250" to="250">fol. 124v</locus>
                <minDesc>Evangelist, Mark, Portrait: Mark writing, seated on bench; buildings in background.</minDesc></minItem> 
            <minItem n="3"> 
            <locus from ="386" to="386">fol. 192v</locus>
                <minDesc>Evangelist, Luke, Portrait: Luke writing, seated on bench before writing desk.</minDesc></minItem>
            <minItem n="4">
                <locus from ="390" to="390">fol. 194v</locus>
                <minDesc>Evangelist, Luke, Portrait: Luke reading, seated on bench; buildings in background.</minDesc></minItem>
             <minItem n="5"> 
            <locus from ="624" to="624">fol. 311v</locus>
                 <minDesc>Evangelist, John, Portrait: John reading book on lectern, seated in high-backed chair.</minDesc></minItem>
            <minItem n="6">
                <locus from ="628" to="628">fol. 313v</locus>
                <minDesc>Evangelist, John, Portrait: John reading, seated on bench before desk; mouth of cave in background.</minDesc></minItem></miniatures>
        <canonTables>
            <p>Citations of concordant gospel sections are framed by architectural columns. These support arched headpieces of multi-colored floral, foliate, and geometric designs. 
                Drawings of lions in red added to the headpiece of the first table.</p>
        </canonTables>
        <headpieces><p>Headpiece of Matthew (fol. 12r), square panel topped with two peacocks; central roundel, Christ in Majesty, right hand raised in blessing. Four 
            creatures (angel, eagle, ox, and lion) in small roundels, one in each corner. Headpieces of the other Evangelists embellished with 
            floral, foliate, and geometric motifs in blue, red, and gold at each gospel opening (fols. 125r, 195r, and 314r).</p>
        </headpieces>
        <initials>
            <p>Beta, the major initial of Matthew, is formed from intertwined figures of men and animals (35-40 mm). Zacharias the priest holding a censer represents the epsilon 
                of Luke's opening. The initials of Mark and John are not decorated (20-25 mm). Minor initials in red set off from the text.</p>
        </initials>
        </decoration>
    <physDesc>
 <support><p><material>Parchment</material> and <material>paper</material>. <dimensions type="block" units="mm">200 x 140 mm</dimensions>.</p></support>
        <extent>401 leaves, of which 1 is a partially raised pastedown and two are flyleaves of paper that function as Easter tables.</extent>
        <foliation><p>1 (unfoliated paper pastedown) + 2 (foliated paper flyleaves) + 398. Modern foliation in Arabic numerals in pencil 1-400.</p></foliation>
        <collation><p>49 quires of 8 leaves, with the exception of quire 48 of 6 leaves, quires 15, 30, and 37 of 7 leaves, and quires 1 and 49 of 10 leaves. Estimate of content lost: 
            leaf 10 of quire 1 and a bifolium (after fol. 11, original and later portraits of Matthew); 1 leaf of quire 15 (after fol. 121, kephalaia of Mark).</p> 
            <p>A second set of 4 Evangelist portraits was added at an unknown date, and 3 leaves of paper containing tables to determine the dates of Easter.</p></collation>
        <dimensions type="written" units="mm">Written space 150 x 105 mm (fol. 29r).</dimensions> 
        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="16-20"><p>1 column, 16 to 20 lines. Ruling with hard point. Lines previously ruled on the bifolium fols. 141 and 148 stand 
            at right angles to the lines of the later ruling pattern.</p></layout>
        <msWriting><handDesc script="Minuscule" medium="ink"><p>Written in minuscule script in black to dark brown ink (some flaking).</p>
            <p>Punctuation includes middle point, comma, marks of elision and interrogation. Quotation marks in left margin next to each line of quoted text.</p></handDesc>
        </msWriting>
        <textDivisions><p>Titles and lectionary indicators αρχε (beginning) and τελος (end) in red.</p></textDivisions>
        <condition><p>Leaves trimmed resulting in the loss of some text. Moderately cockled. Dirt and water stains.</p></condition>
        <bindingDesc>
            <binding><p>Bound in red <material>velvet</material> over boards. Floral-patterned edge decoration, fore-edge in blue. Doublures (one remaining, back) of 
                woven cloth in a diagonal pattern of rose, white, blue, and yellow, bordered with strips of rose silk glued down.</p></binding></bindingDesc>
 </physDesc>
    <history><origin><p>The manuscript may have been written in the <name reg="Balkan Peninsula" type="place">Balkan Peninsula</name> to judge from certain of the inscriptions, and in either the 12th or 13th century.</p></origin> 
    <provenance><p>Medieval to late 17th century provenance unknown. Contains dated and undated colophons and inscriptions in Greek and Church Slavonic.</p>
        <p><name reg="Kosma" type="person" role="monk">Kosma</name>, a hieromonk of <name reg=" Monastery of Chilandari (Mount Athos, Greece)" type="org">Hilandar</name>, the Serbian monastery  
            on <name reg="Mount Athos, Greece" type="place">Mount Athos</name>, restored the manuscript when it belonged to the <name reg="Church of St. George (Pološko)" type="org">Church of St. George, Pološko</name>, which today is 
            located near <name reg="Kavadarci, Macedonia" type="place">Kavadarci</name> in the <name reg="Macedonia" type="place"> Republic of Macedonia</name> (undated inscription written 
            by <name reg="Michael the Painter" type="person" role="artist">Michael the Painter</name>; prayer of Kosma, fol. 9v).</p>
        <p>The manuscript was in the possession of <name reg="Chekhra" type="person" role="monk">Chekhra</name>, chief monk of Kovin, who documented the transfer of his authority over the 
            <name reg="Church of St. Nicholas (Kovin)" type="org">Church of St. Nicholas</name> to the Bishop <name reg="Nicholas" type="person" role="bishop">Nicholas</name> in an undated inscription (fol. 400v).</p>
        <p>At the end of the 17th century, the book was rebound and restored by the hieromonk <name reg="Chrysanthus, 17th century" type="person" role="monk">Chrysanthus</name>, whose inscription notes that he took it 
            from a Turkish-controlled area of <name reg="Iberia" type="place">Iberia</name>, the present-day nation of <name reg="Georgia" type="place">Georgia</name> (his inscription, fol. 2v). Both Chrysanthus's inscription and 
            a second unsigned writing dated 11 February 1700 (fol. 123v) include the name Τζηλτηρε, a geographic area as yet unidentified.</p>
        <p>The monk Kosma's signature with two gospel citations (fol. 10r); inscription of <name reg="Gerasim" type="person">Gerasim</name> (fol. 400v, undated); prayer of <name reg="Singchoreseos" type="person" role="monk">Singchoreseos</name> 
            (front pastedown, recto, undated); unsigned and undated inscriptions and prayers (fols. 4r, 6r, 122r, 147r, 400v). Drawings of birds (front pastedown, verso).</p></provenance>
        <acquisition><p>Acquired by the University of Chicago in 1929 from <name reg="Riefstahl, Rudolf Meyer, 1880-1936" type="person" role="antiquarian">Rudolf M. Riefstahl</name> 
            (New York), with funds provided by <name reg="Woodward, Frederic Campbell, 1874-1954" type="person" role="donor">Frederic C. Woodward</name>, 
            university vice-president, <name reg="Matthews, Shailer, 1863-1941" type="person" role="donor">Shailer Matthews</name>, dean of the Divinity School, calligrapher and illuminator 
            <name reg="Ricketts, Coella Lindsay, 1859-1941" type="person" role="donor">Coella Lindsay Ricketts</name>, and real estate 
            developer <name reg="Galt, Arthur T., born 1876" type="person" role="donor">Arthur T. Galt</name>.</p></acquisition>
</history>
    <additional><listBibl><bibl><author>Samuel A. Cartledge</author>, 
            <title level="u">"A group of Gospels manuscripts"</title> 
            <note>(Ph.D. diss., University of Chicago, 1930).</note></bibl>
            <bibl><author>Seymour de Ricci,</author>
                <title level="m">Census of Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts in the United States and Canada</title>.
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>(New York:</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>H. W. Wilson Company,</publisher>
                    <date>1935),</date>
                </imprint>
                <biblScope type="volume">vol. 1, p. 569.</biblScope></bibl>
            <bibl><author>Kenneth W. Clark</author>, 
                <title level="m">A Descriptive Catalogue of Greek New Testament Manuscripts in America</title>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>(Chicago:</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>University of Chicago Press,</publisher>
                    <date>1937),</date>
                </imprint>
                <biblScope type="pages">pp. 235-238.</biblScope></bibl>
        <bibl> 
            <author>Harold Rideout Willoughby</author>, 
            <title level="a">"Greek Rebinding Colophons in Chicago Manuscripts,"</title> 
            <title level="j">Annales de l'institut Kondakov</title> 
            <biblScope type="volume">11</biblScope> 
            <imprint><date>(1940),</date></imprint> 
            <biblScope type="pages">pp. 24-27, 29.</biblScope></bibl>
            <bibl>
                <author>Merrill Mead Parvis</author>, 
                <title level="m">The Story of the Goodspeed Collection</title>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>([Chicago]:</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                    <date>1952),</date>
                </imprint>
                <biblScope type="pages">p. 8.</biblScope></bibl>
        <bibl>
            <author>Djurdje Bošković</author>,
            <title level="a">"O nekim našim graditeljima i slikarima iz prvih decenija XIV veka,"</title>
            <title level="j">Starinar</title> 
            <biblScope type="volume">9/10</biblScope> 
            <imprint><date>(1958-1959),</date></imprint> 
            <biblScope type="pages">pp. 125-131.</biblScope>
        </bibl>
        <bibl><author>Gordana Babić</author>, 
            <title level="a">"Srpski zapisi u grčkom četvorojevandjelju br. 131 iz Čikaga (SAD) = 
                Les inscriptions serbs du tétraévangile grec No 131, conservé à Chicago,"</title> in 
            <title level="m">Zbornik za likovnu umetnost</title>
            <imprint>
                <pubPlace>(Novi Sad (Serbia):</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Matica srpska,</publisher>
                <date>1972),</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope type="volume">8,</biblScope>
            <biblScope type="pages">pp. 361-371.</biblScope></bibl>
        <bibl> 
            <title level="m">New Testament manuscript traditions. An exhibition based on the Edgar J. Goodspeed 
                Collection of the University of Chicago Library, the Joseph Regenstein Library, January-March, 1973</title>. 
            <title level="s">University of Chicago. Library. Dept. of Special Collections. Exhibition catalogs</title>
            <imprint> 
                <pubPlace>([Chicago:</pubPlace> 
                <publisher>s.n.,</publisher> 
                <date>1973]),</date></imprint> 
            <biblScope type="volume">36,</biblScope> 
            <biblScope type="catalogNo">no. 52.</biblScope></bibl></listBibl> 
    </additional>
            </msDescription>
        </body>
    </text>      
</TEI.2>
