<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//DLDC//DTD Revised TEI DTD for Goodspeed Manuscript Project//EN"
"http://dldc.lib.uchicago.edu/DTD/goodspeed.dtd">
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader date.created="2015-11-04" creator="jfcd">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 <title>[University of Chicago Library GMS-0949,  a manuscript catalogue description in electronic form]</title>
 <funder>Institute of Museum and Library Services</funder>
 <respStmt>
  <resp>Creation of electronic version:</resp>
  <name>University of Chicago Library</name>
  <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
  <name>University of Chicago Library</name>
 </respStmt> 
</titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
  <publisher>University of Chicago Library, Special Collections Research Center</publisher>
  <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
  <date>2009</date>
  <idno type="Local">http://pi.lib.uchicago.edu/1001/dig/gms/0949</idno>
  <availability status= "free">
   <p>Publicly accessible</p></availability>
 </publicationStmt>
 <sourceDesc>
 <msDescription>
  <msIdentifier>
   <country>United States</country>
   <region>Illinois</region>
   <settlement>Chicago</settlement>
   <institution>University of Chicago Library</institution> 
   <repository>Special Collections Research Center</repository>
   <collection>Goodspeed Manuscript Collection</collection>
   <idno>Ms. 949</idno>
   <altIdentifier type="former shelfmark">Goodspeed Ms. Arm. 47</altIdentifier>
  </msIdentifier>
  <msHeading>
   <title>New Testament. Gospels</title>
   <otherName>Red Gospels of Ganjasar</otherName>
   <origPlace>Armenia</origPlace>
   <origDate notBefore="1101" notAfter="1300">12th or 13th century</origDate>
   <textLang langKey="hye">Armenian</textLang>
  </msHeading>
  <msContents>
   <overview><p>Four gospels in Armenian. Section numbers in the margins against the text. Concordance numbers 
    in the lower margins. Pentecostal lection numbers. Formerly Goodspeed Ms. Arm. 47.</p>
    <p>The Red Gospels of Ganjasar, as the manuscript is commonly known, was named both for the predominant red pigment of its miniatures, 
     and for the monastery in which its two earliest-known owners lived as members of the community.</p></overview></msContents>
  <decoration>
   <overview><p>11 full-page miniatures consist of portraits of the Evangelists (Matthew lost), and depictions of events from the life of Christ painted by the artist Abas 
    (his undated signature, fols. 4r, 139v).</p> <p>Marginal vignettes of arabesques, floral designs, birds, and 3 miniatures, Harvester (fol. 179r), Christ riding a donkey (fol. 213r); 
     and a boy in a tree (fol. 280r).</p></overview>
   <canonTables><p>Citations of concordant gospel sections are framed by architectural columns. These support headpieces of floral, foliate, 
    and geometric designs, on which large birds (peacocks?) stand. Signatures of Ignatios and Yovsep‛, the artist and his pupil who created the tables, 
    and a prayer that the lord remember them (fol. 13r).</p>
   </canonTables> 
   <headpieces><p>The headpiece of Mark's gospel opening contains an image of the <hi rend="italics">Deesis</hi>, Christ 
    enthroned, the Virgin Mary on his right, and John the Baptist at his left (fol. 85r). Headpieces of Luke and 
    John's gospel openings are of multi-colored floral, foliate, and interlace motifs (fols. 140r, 238r). Marginal arabesques (200-215 mm).</p>
   </headpieces> 
   <initials><p>The major initials of Mark (60 mm), Luke (145 mm), and John's (215 mm) gospel 
    openings are formed by multi-colored floral, foliate, and interlace motifs.</p>
   </initials></decoration>
  <physDesc>
   <support><p><material>Parchment</material>. <dimensions type="block" units="mm">265 x 200 mm</dimensions>.</p></support> 
   <extent>316 leaves, of which 2 are flyleaves. The leaf following fol. 295, overlooked during the manuscript's initial foliation, has been designated fol. 295b. 
    Flyleaves conjoint with pastedowns.</extent> 
   <foliation><p>1 (unfoliated parchment flyleaf) + 295 + 1 + 18 + 1 (unfoliated paper flyleaf). Modern foliation in Arabic numerals in pencil 1-313.</p></foliation> 
   <dimensions type="written" units="mm">Written space 215 x 135 mm (fol. 90r). Each column is 215 x 60 mm with a space of 15 mm between.</dimensions> 
   <layout columns="2" writtenLines="19-20 per column"><p>2 columns of 19 to 20 lines. Ruling with hard point.</p></layout> 
   <msWriting><handDesc script="Erkat’agir" medium="ink"> 
    <p>Written in erkat’agir script in black ink.</p></handDesc></msWriting>
   <textDivisions><p>Titles in red.</p></textDivisions>
   <condition><p>Several miniatures have suffered water damage which caused pigment to run. Edges of all leaves are dry 
    and some are cracked. Lower corners of a number of leaves have been reinforced. Margins were trimmed presumably during rebinding, 
    thus marring a number of miniatures and vignettes. Dirt and grease stains.</p></condition> 
   <bindingDesc>
    <binding><p>Bound in dark brown <material>leather</material> over boards. Nail holes and several silver nails remain along outer edge.</p>
     <decoNote><p>Covers (front and back) blind tooled in a repeating geometric pattern of diamonds with 
      stamped rosettes at main points. Central motif set within a narrow rectilinear rosette-filled frame.</p></decoNote></binding>
   </bindingDesc>
  </physDesc>
  <history>
   <origin><p>The manuscript is judged to have been written and illuminated in either the 12th or 13th century in <name reg="Armenia" type="place">Armenia</name>, 
    possibly at <name reg="Ani" type="place">Ani</name>, an historic site now located in <name reg="Turkey" type="place">Turkey</name>. 
    The artist <name reg="Abas, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Abas</name>, who painted the miniatures, signed the scene of Christ's 
    Transfiguration (fol. 4r), and the Evangelist Luke's portrait (fol. 139v) in Greek and Georgian. To the latter image, he added a third 
    signature in Armenian, and a prayer. The painters who created the canon tables, <name reg="Ignatios, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Ignatios</name> and 
    his pupil <name reg="Yovsep‛, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Yovsep‛</name>, added signatures and a brief prayer (fol. 13r).</p></origin>
   <provenance>
    <p>According to the oldest extant colophon (fols. 311r-313v) dated 1237 (Armenian Era 686), the manuscript was acquired by the 
     brothers <name reg="Grigor, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Grigor</name> and <name reg="Vardan, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Vardan</name>, 
     who were priests under Abbot <name reg="Yovhanēs, Abbot, 13th century" type="person" role="abbot">Yovhanēs</name> at  the 
     <name reg="Monastery of Ganjasar (Armenia)" type="org">Monastery of Ganjasar</name> in the Xach‛en Canton of  Armenia's Arts‛akh Province. 
     Prayers recorded for Grigor and Vardan (fols. 83v, 139r, 236v).</p> 
    <p>An agreement  (fol. 3r) dated 1281 (Armenian Era 730) between <name reg="Marcpan, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Marcpan</name> 
     and <name reg="Mamikon, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Mamikon</name> and the clergy of 
     the <name reg="Monastery of the Holy Theotokos (Shikayk‛ar)" type="org">Monastery of the Holy Theotokos (Surb Astuacacin)</name> 
     at <name reg="Shikayk‛ar" type="place">Shikayk‛ar</name> indicates the former were owners who donated the manuscript to the monastic foundation in exchange 
     for the celebration of masses in memory of certain family members. Those named include <name reg="Hasan" type="person">Hasan</name>, 
     <name reg="Sewadē" type="person">Sewadē</name>, and <name reg="Mamaxat‛un" type="person">Mamaxat‛un</name>.</p>
    <p>The inscription of <name reg="Yakobeanc‛, Xach‛luec‛i Yovanēs Baghtasar" type="person" role="owner">Xach‛luec‛i Yovanēs Baghtasar Yakobeanc‛</name>, 
     dated December 20, 1915, recounts the manuscript's capture and his recovery of it from the Kurdish village of 
     <name reg="Haytar-Ōghli" type="place">Haytar-Ōghli</name>. Also described is the flight of Armenian residents 
     from <name reg="Alashkert" type="place">Alashkert</name>, the present-day <name reg="Eleskirt, Turkey" type="place">Eleskirt, Turkey</name>, 
     to the village of <name reg="Gēch‛rlu" type="place">Gēch‛rlu</name> (fol. 236v).</p>
    <p>Belonged to <name reg="Dawit‛ean, Mushegh" type="person" role="owner">Mushegh Dawit‛ean</name> who purchased the manuscript 
     at Alashkert from Xach‛luec‛i Yakobeanc‛ for 10 Russian rubles on July 7, 1916. Additionally, he states that Turks had captured it 
     in 1914 during one of the Russo-Turkish conflicts (his inscription, fol. 83v).</p>
    <p>On an unknown date, the priest <name reg="Hayrakan" type="person" role="owner">Hayrakan</name> bought the manuscript 
     for "one red ox and many other things," from <name reg="Sewaday" type="person" role="owner">Sewaday</name>, son of Vaxtank. Hayrakan's 
     grandfather (of the same name) had formerly owned the manuscript, and it is noted, "evil hands" destroyed his colophon (fols. 236v-237r).</p>
    <p>Bishop <name reg="Sargis" type="person" role="bishop">Sargis</name> wrote an inscription for the priest 
     <name reg="Eghiay" type="person" role="owner">Eghiay</name>, who purchased the manuscript as a memorial to his soul and those of his 
     parents <name reg="Martiros" type="person">Martiros</name> and <name reg="Jumli" type="person">Jumli</name> (fol. 139v).</p>
    <p>Belonged also to <name reg="Gharberdec‛i, Xawch‛a Sawar" type="person" role="owner">Xawch‛a Sawar Gharberdec‛i</name>, son of 
     <name reg="Astuacatur" type="person">Astuacatur</name> and <name reg="Kulshat" type="person">Kulshat</name>. In his undated 
     inscription (fol. 84r), Gharberdec‛i refers to a famine and plague in the city of <name reg="Karuc‛" type="place">Karuc‛</name>, the present-day 
     <name reg="Kars, Turkey" type="place">Kars, Turkey</name>, where he may have resided.</p>
    <p>Other entries consist of brief prayers (fols. 8v, 15r), an inscription dated 1275 (Armenian Era 724) (fol. 15v), and partially 
     legible notation (fols. 2v, 4v, 5v, 6r, 11v, 12r, 16r). University of Chicago Libraries bookplate and description summary (front pastedown).</p></provenance> 
   <acquisition><p>Acquired by the University of Chicago 
    from <name reg="R. Stora and Company (Firm)" type="org" role="bookseller">R. Stora and Company</name> (New York), September 1941.
   </p></acquisition>
  </history>
 </msDescription>
 </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
 <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
   <p>The Edgar J. Goodspeed Manuscript Collection contains 68 Greek, Armenian, Latin, Syriac, Ethiopic, and 
    Arabic manuscripts, which range in date from the fifth to the nineteenth century. With support from the Institute 
    of Museum and Library Services National Leadership Grants for Libraries, Building Digital Resources program, 
    the University of Chicago Library has created the online Goodspeed Manuscript Collection, a unique digital 
    resource with manuscripts digitized in their entirety and presented with high-quality zoomable images through 
    an interface that supports browsing within individual manuscripts and across the collection.</p>
   <p>Descriptions of the manuscripts have been encoded using the standard set forth in TEI Consortium, eds., <title>TEI P5 Guidelines for Electronic 
    Text Encoding and Interchange: Manuscript Description</title>, at <ref>http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html</ref> 
    as of <date>2012-09-22</date>.</p> 
   <p>The TEI DTD used was obtained from the Digital Scriptorium of Columbia University 
    at, <ref>https://www1.columbia.edu/sec/cu/libraries/bts/digital_scriptorium/technical/ds-xml/description_dtd/index.html</ref> on <date>2012-09-22</date>. To 
    accommodate specific project needs, the DTD was edited and extended with local tags in order to describe the content of miniatures, 
    and the structure of canon tables, headpieces, and initials. The process of editing included equating the element Decoration with the seven 
    recognized elements of the TEI Manuscript Description, not only to emphasize intellectual substance, but also to augment 
    visibility by providing links from the record through encoding to the digitized imagery of the Web display.</p> 
  </projectDesc>
 </encodingDesc>
 <profileDesc>
 <langUsage><language id="hye"></language><p>Armenian, ISO 639-3</p>
 </langUsage>
  <textClass>
   <keywords>
    <term>Bible. N.T. Gospels. Armenian</term>
    <term>Manuscripts, Armenian</term>
    <term>Illuminated manuscripts</term>
    <term>Miniatures (Illuminations)</term>
    <term>Abas, 12th century-13th century</term>
   </keywords>
  </textClass>
 </profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
 <text>
 <body>
 <msDescription id="GMS-0949">
 <msIdentifier>
 <country>United States</country>
<region>Illinois</region>
 <settlement>Chicago</settlement>
 <institution>University of Chicago Library</institution> 
 <repository>Special Collections Research Center</repository>
 <collection>Goodspeed Manuscript Collection</collection>
 <idno>Ms. 949</idno>
<altIdentifier type="former shelfmark">Goodspeed Ms. Arm. 47</altIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
<msHeading>
 <title>New Testament. Gospels</title>
 <otherName>Red Gospels of Ganjasar</otherName>
 <origPlace>Armenia</origPlace>
 <origDate notBefore="1101" notAfter="1300">12th or 13th century</origDate>
<textLang langKey="hye">Armenian</textLang>
</msHeading>
 <msContents>
  <overview><p>Four gospels in Armenian. Section numbers in the margins against the text. Concordance numbers 
   in the lower margins. Pentecostal lection numbers. Formerly Goodspeed Ms. Arm. 47.</p>
   <p>The Red Gospels of Ganjasar, as the manuscript is commonly known, was named both for the predominant red pigment of its miniatures, 
    and for the monastery in which its two earliest-known owners lived as members of the community</p></overview>
 <msItem n="1">
  <locus from="009" to="009">fol. 3r</locus> <additions><p>Agreement (fragmentary) for the celebration of masses, dated 1281 (Armenian Era 730).</p></additions>
  <note>Blank (fols. 1r, 7v-8r).</note>
 </msItem> 
  <msItem n="2">
   <locus from="020" to="034">fols. 8v-15v</locus>
   <summary>Canon tables have been bound out of order. For the correct sequence: I-II (fols. 10v-11r); III-IV (fols. 8v-9r); V-VII (fols. 12v-13r); 
    VIII-X (fols. 14v-15r).</summary>
   <note>Blank (fols. 9v-10r, 13v-14r).</note>
  </msItem> 
  <msItem n="3">
   <locus from="037" to="171">fols. 17r-84r</locus>
   <summary>Matthew (gospel begins with the last word of 8:34).</summary>
  </msItem> 
  <msItem n="4">
   <locus from="173" to="281">fols. 85r-139r</locus>
   <summary>Mark.</summary>
  </msItem> 
  <msItem n="5">
   <locus from="283" to="477">fols. 140r-237r</locus>
   <summary>Luke. </summary>
  </msItem> 
  <msItem n="6">
   <locus from="479" to="625">fols. 238r-310r</locus>
   <summary>John.</summary></msItem> 
  <msItem n="7">
   <locus from="625" to="626">fols. 310r-310v</locus>
   <summary>Pericope: The Woman taken in Adultery.</summary>
  </msItem> 
  <msItem n="8">
   <locus from="627" to="632">fols. 311r-313v</locus>
   <colophon>Description of the manuscript's acquisition by the brothers Grigor and 
    Vardan, dated 1237 (lacking).</colophon>
  </msItem> 
  </msContents>
  <decoration>
   <overview><p>11 full-page miniatures consist of portraits of the Evangelists (Matthew lost), and depictions of events from the life of Christ painted by the artist Abas 
    (his undated signature, fols. 4r, 139v).</p> <p>Marginal vignettes of arabesques, floral designs, birds, and 3 miniatures, Harvester (fol. 179r), Christ riding a donkey (fol. 213r); 
     and a boy in a tree (fol. 280r).</p></overview>
  <miniatures>
   <minItem n="1">
  <locus from ="006" to="006">fol. 1v</locus>
<minDesc>Virgin Mary: Annunciation. Virgin Mary seated, foreground right; angel stands, at left.</minDesc> 
  <note>Blank (fol. 1r).</note></minItem>
 <minItem n="2">
  <locus from ="007" to="007">fol. 2r</locus>
  <minDesc>Scenes displayed in 5 registers. Christ: Nativity. Virgin Mary lies on pallet inside stable, foreground; Christ Child in manger next to her, 
   nuzzled by ox and donkey; six angels in background. Magi: Adoration. Midwives bathe Christ Child, at 
   right, star overhead; Joseph dreams, seated on floor at left; three magi, at center, flanked by angels, approach Christ Child 
   carrying gifts. Shepherds: Beholding star. Shepherd plays pipe, at right; other shepherds gaze skyward; flock of sheep below them.
  </minDesc></minItem>
 <minItem n="3">
  <locus from ="010" to="010">fol. 3v</locus>
  <minDesc>Christ: Baptism. John the Baptist on riverbank at left, baptizes Christ, standing in river; dove of Holy Spirit descends from hand of 
   God extended from star-filled sky; disciples and angels on either bank, in background.</minDesc></minItem>
 <minItem n="4">
  <locus from ="011" to="011">fol. 4r</locus>
  <minDesc>Christ: Transfiguration. Christ, at center, on mountain within star-filled mandorla, Elijah at left, 
   Moses to the right; disciples Peter, James, and John, in foreground below.</minDesc>
  <additions><p>Signature of the artist Abas.</p></additions></minItem>
 <minItem n="5">
  <locus from ="013" to="013">fol. 5r</locus>
  <minDesc>Christ: Entry into Jerusalem. Christ, seated on donkey led by disciple; other disciples, at right; in foreground, people lay robes in 
   Christ's path, others hold palm branches at left; trumpeters playing in city tower, and a crowd watches from Jerusalem's walls in background.</minDesc> 
  <additions><p>Inscription, illegible (fol. 5v).</p></additions></minItem>
 <minItem n="6">
  <locus from ="016" to="016">fol. 6v</locus>
  <minDesc>Christ: Crucifixion. Christ crucified on cross; below him, Virgin Mary and disciple John stand at either side; skull lays on mound at foot of cross; 
   sun, moon, and angels above cross-arms; at left of scene, Church personified, accompanied by angel, holds chalice into which water and blood flow from 
   Christ's wounded side; Synagogue personified, at right with attendant angel, turns away.</minDesc>
  <note>Inscription bordering miniature, in part illegible.</note></minItem>
 <minItem n="7">
  <locus from ="017" to="017">fol. 7r</locus>
  <minDesc>Christ: Ascension. Christ seated within star-filled mandorla ascends to heaven flanked 
   by angels, two of which blow trumpets; Virgin Mary and witnesses stand below the scene, gaze skyward.</minDesc> 
  <note>Blank (fols. 7v-8r).</note></minItem>
 <minItem n="8">
  <locus from ="036" to="036">fol. 16v</locus>
  <minDesc>Evangelist, Matthew: Portrait. Matthew writing, seated on bench; angel symbol above.</minDesc> 
  <additions><p>Inscription, partially illegible (fol. 16r).</p></additions></minItem>
 <minItem n="9">
  <locus from ="172" to="172">fol. 84v</locus>
  <minDesc>Evangelist, Mark: Portrait. Mark writing, seated on bench; lion symbol above.</minDesc></minItem>
<minItem n="10">
  <locus from ="282" to="282">fol. 139v</locus>
 <minDesc>Evangelist, Luke: Portrait. Luke writing, seated on bench; ox symbol above. Prayer: 
 Remember the painter Abas, the unworthy priest</minDesc>
 <additions><p>Signature of the artist Abas.</p></additions></minItem>
  <minItem n="11">
   <locus from ="478" to="478">fol. 237v</locus>
   <minDesc>Evangelist, John: Portrait. John writing, seated on bench; angel stands behind him; 
   eagle symbol above.</minDesc></minItem></miniatures>
   <canonTables><p>Citations of concordant gospel sections are framed by architectural columns. These support headpieces of floral, foliate, 
    and geometric designs, on which large birds (peacocks?) stand. Signatures of Ignatios and Yovsep‛, the artist and his pupil who created the tables, 
    and a prayer that the lord remember them (fol. 13r).</p>
 </canonTables> 
 <headpieces><p>The headpiece of Mark's gospel opening contains an image of the <hi rend="italics">Deesis</hi>, Christ 
  enthroned, the Virgin Mary on his right, and John the Baptist at his left (fol. 85r). Headpieces of Luke and 
  John's gospel openings are of multi-colored floral, foliate, and interlace motifs (fols. 140r, 238r). Marginal arabesques (200-215 mm).</p>
 </headpieces> 
 <initials><p>The major initials of Mark (60 mm), Luke (145 mm), and John's (215 mm) gospel 
  openings are formed by multi-colored floral, foliate, and interlace motifs.</p>
 </initials>
 <comments><p>Church, a metaphorical figure in the scene of Christ's crucifixion (fol. 6v),  
  captures in a single chalice blood and water pouring in separate streams from the wound in Christ's 
  side. It has been argued that this depiction is representative of the liturgical practice of the Georgian and Greek 
  churches in which Eucharistic wine and water are mixed, rather than Armenian practice in which 
  wine and water are kept separate. (Alice Taylor, "Armenian Illumination under Georgian, Turkish, and 
  Mongol Rule," in <hi rend="italics">Treasures in heaven: Armenian illuminated manuscripts</hi>, pp. 85-103).
 </p></comments>
</decoration>
<physDesc>
<support><p><material>Parchment</material>. <dimensions type="block" units="mm">265 x 200 mm</dimensions>.</p></support> 
 <extent>316 leaves, of which 2 are flyleaves. The leaf following fol. 295, overlooked during the manuscript's initial foliation, has been designated fol. 295b. 
  Flyleaves conjoint with pastedowns.</extent> 
 <foliation><p>1 (unfoliated parchment flyleaf) + 295 + 1 + 18 + 1 (unfoliated paper flyleaf). Modern foliation in Arabic numerals in pencil 1-313.</p></foliation> 
 <dimensions type="written" units="mm">Written space 215 x 135 mm (fol. 90r). Each column is 215 x 60 mm with a space of 15 mm between.</dimensions> 
 <layout columns="2" writtenLines="19-20 per column"><p>2 columns of 19 to 20 lines. Ruling with hard point.</p></layout> 
 <msWriting><handDesc script="Erkat’agir" medium="ink"> 
  <p>Written in erkat’agir script in black ink.</p></handDesc></msWriting>
 <textDivisions><p>Titles in red.</p></textDivisions>
 <condition><p>Several miniatures have suffered water damage which caused pigment to run. Edges of all leaves are dry 
  and some are cracked. Lower corners of a number of leaves have been reinforced. Margins were trimmed presumably during rebinding, 
  thus marring a number of miniatures and vignettes. Dirt and grease stains.</p></condition> 
 <bindingDesc>
  <binding><p>Bound in dark brown <material>leather</material> over boards. Nail holes and several silver nails remain along outer edge.</p>
   <decoNote><p>Covers (front and back) blind tooled in a repeating geometric pattern of diamonds with 
    stamped rosettes at main points. Central motif set within a narrow rectilinear rosette-filled frame.</p></decoNote></binding>
 </bindingDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
 <origin><p>The manuscript is judged to have been written and illuminated in either the 12th or 13th century in <name reg="Armenia" type="place">Armenia</name>, 
  possibly at <name reg="Ani" type="place">Ani</name>, an historic site now located in <name reg="Turkey" type="place">Turkey</name>. 
  The artist <name reg="Abas, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Abas</name>, who painted the miniatures, signed the scene of Christ's 
  Transfiguration (fol. 4r), and the Evangelist Luke's portrait (fol. 139v) in Greek and Georgian. To the latter image, he added a third 
  signature in Armenian, and a prayer. The painters who created the canon tables, <name reg="Ignatios, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Ignatios</name> and 
  his pupil <name reg="Yovsep‛, 12th century-13th century" type="person" role="artist">Yovsep‛</name>, added signatures and a brief prayer (fol. 13r).</p></origin>
 <provenance>
  <p>According to the oldest extant colophon (fols. 311r-313v) dated 1237 (Armenian Era 686), the manuscript was acquired by the 
   brothers <name reg="Grigor, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Grigor</name> and <name reg="Vardan, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Vardan</name>, 
   who were priests under Abbot <name reg="Yovhanēs, Abbot, 13th century" type="person" role="abbot">Yovhanēs</name> at  the 
  <name reg="Monastery of Ganjasar (Armenia)" type="org">Monastery of Ganjasar</name> in the Xach‛en Canton of  Armenia's Arts‛akh Province. 
  Prayers recorded for Grigor and Vardan (fols. 83v, 139r, 236v).</p> 
  <p>An agreement  (fol. 3r) dated 1281 (Armenian Era 730) between <name reg="Marcpan, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Marcpan</name> 
   and <name reg="Mamikon, 13th century" type="person" role="owner">Mamikon</name> and the clergy of 
   the <name reg="Monastery of the Holy Theotokos (Shikayk‛ar)" type="org">Monastery of the Holy Theotokos (Surb Astuacacin)</name> 
   at <name reg="Shikayk‛ar" type="place">Shikayk‛ar</name> indicates the former were owners who donated the manuscript to the monastic foundation in exchange 
   for the celebration of masses in memory of certain family members. Those named include <name reg="Hasan" type="person">Hasan</name>, 
   <name reg="Sewadē" type="person">Sewadē</name>, and <name reg="Mamaxat‛un" type="person">Mamaxat‛un</name>.</p>
  <p>The inscription of <name reg="Yakobeanc‛, Xach‛luec‛i Yovanēs Baghtasar" type="person" role="owner">Xach‛luec‛i Yovanēs Baghtasar Yakobeanc‛</name>, 
   dated December 20, 1915, recounts the manuscript's capture and his recovery of it from the Kurdish village of 
   <name reg="Haytar-Ōghli" type="place">Haytar-Ōghli</name>. Also described is the flight of Armenian residents 
   from <name reg="Alashkert" type="place">Alashkert</name>, the present-day <name reg="Eleskirt, Turkey" type="place">Eleskirt, Turkey</name>, 
   to the village of <name reg="Gēch‛rlu" type="place">Gēch‛rlu</name> (fol. 236v).</p>
  <p>Belonged to <name reg="Dawit‛ean, Mushegh" type="person" role="owner">Mushegh Dawit‛ean</name> who purchased the manuscript 
   at Alashkert from Xach‛luec‛i Yakobeanc‛ for 10 Russian rubles on July 7, 1916. Additionally, he states that Turks had captured it 
   in 1914 during one of the Russo-Turkish conflicts (his inscription, fol. 83v).</p>
 <p>On an unknown date, the priest <name reg="Hayrakan" type="person" role="owner">Hayrakan</name> bought the manuscript 
  for "one red ox and many other things," from <name reg="Sewaday" type="person" role="owner">Sewaday</name>, son of Vaxtank. Hayrakan's 
    grandfather (of the same name) had formerly owned the manuscript, and it is noted, "evil hands" destroyed his colophon (fols. 236v-237r).</p>
  <p>Bishop <name reg="Sargis" type="person" role="bishop">Sargis</name> wrote an inscription for the priest 
   <name reg="Eghiay" type="person" role="owner">Eghiay</name>, who purchased the manuscript as a memorial to his soul and those of his 
   parents <name reg="Martiros" type="person">Martiros</name> and <name reg="Jumli" type="person">Jumli</name> (fol. 139v).</p>
  <p>Belonged also to <name reg="Gharberdec‛i, Xawch‛a Sawar" type="person" role="owner">Xawch‛a Sawar Gharberdec‛i</name>, son of 
   <name reg="Astuacatur" type="person">Astuacatur</name> and <name reg="Kulshat" type="person">Kulshat</name>. In his undated 
   inscription (fol. 84r), Gharberdec‛i refers to a famine and plague in the city of <name reg="Karuc‛" type="place">Karuc‛</name>, the present-day 
   <name reg="Kars, Turkey" type="place">Kars, Turkey</name>, where he may have resided.</p>
  <p>Other entries consist of brief prayers (fols. 8v, 15r), an inscription dated 1275 (Armenian Era 724) (fol. 15v), and partially 
   legible notation (fols. 2v, 4v, 5v, 6r, 11v, 12r, 16r). University of Chicago Libraries bookplate and description summary (front pastedown).</p></provenance> 
<acquisition><p>Acquired by the University of Chicago 
 from <name reg="R. Stora and Company (Firm)" type="org" role="bookseller">R. Stora and Company</name> (New York), September 1941.
 </p></acquisition>
</history>
<additional><listBibl><bibl>
 <author>Sirarpie Der Nersessian</author>, 
 <title level="a">"Armenian Gospel Illustration as seen in manuscripts in American Collections,"</title> in 
 <title level="m">New Testament Manuscript studies: the materials and the making of a critical apparatus</title> edited by 
 <editor>Merrill M. Parvis</editor> and <editor>Allen P. Wikgren</editor>. 
 <imprint> 
  <pubPlace>(Chicago:</pubPlace> 
  <publisher>University of Chicago Press,</publisher> 
  <date>c1950),</date>
 </imprint> 
 <biblScope type="pages">pp. 140-141, and pl. II.</biblScope>
</bibl> 
 <bibl><author>Merrill Mead Parvis</author>, 
  <title level="m">The Story of the Goodspeed Collection</title>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>([Chicago:]</pubPlace>
 <publisher>s.n.,</publisher> 
<date>1952),</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="pages">pp. 25-26.</biblScope></bibl>
 <bibl>
  <author>Erroll F. Rhodes</author>, 
  <title level="m">An Annotated List of Armenian New Testament Manuscripts</title>, 
  <title level="s">Annual Report of Theology</title>
  <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
  <imprint><date>(1959),</date></imprint>
  <biblScope type="pages">p. 134 (1038).</biblScope></bibl>
 <bibl> 
  <title level="m">New Testament manuscript traditions. An exhibition based on the Edgar J. Goodspeed 
  Collection of the University of Chicago Library, the Joseph Regenstein Library, January-March, 1973</title>. 
  <title level="s">University of Chicago. Library. Dept. of Special Collections. Exhibition catalogs</title>
  <imprint> 
   <pubPlace>([Chicago:</pubPlace> 
   <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>  
   <date>1973]),</date></imprint> 
  <biblScope type="volume">36,</biblScope> 
  <biblScope type="catalogNo">no. 66.</biblScope></bibl>
 <bibl>
  <author>Avedis K. Sanjian</author>, 
  <title level="m">A catalogue of medieval Armenian manuscripts in the United States</title>
  <imprint>
   <pubPlace>(Berkeley:</pubPlace>
   <publisher>University of California Press,</publisher>
   <date>1976),</date>
  </imprint>
  <biblScope type="pages">pp. 226-237.</biblScope></bibl>
 <bibl>
  <title level="m">Treasures in heaven: Armenian illuminated manuscripts</title>, edited by 
  <editor>Thomas F. Mathews</editor> and <editor>Roger S. Wieck</editor>
  <imprint>
   <pubPlace>(New York:</pubPlace>
   <publisher>Pierpont Morgan Library; Princeton, N.J.: distributed by Princeton University Press,</publisher>
   <date>1994),</date>
  </imprint>
  <biblScope type="pages">pp. 163-164 (cat. 24).</biblScope></bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
 </msDescription>
 </body>
 </text>    
 </TEI.2>
